Register of the Joshua B. Powers collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Joshua B. Powers collection
1876-1969
68026
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (4.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, telegrams, biographies, articles, pamphlets, clippings, writings, photographs, maps, scrapbooks, and memorabilia relating to Homer Lea, military adviser to Sun Yat-sen and author of The Valor of Ignorance, and to the revolutionary movement in China, circa 1900-1920. Includes writings and correspondence of Homer Lea, Ethel Lea, and Joshua B. Powers.
Powers, Joshua B.
Lea, Ethel
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1968.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Joshua B. Powers
1892 August 25 Born, Owensboro, Kentucky
1911-1913 Student, University of Texas
1926-1972 Representative, La Prensa, Buenos Aires, Argentina, and other publications, New York City Manager, United Press Association, Buenos Aires; chairman of Joshua B. Powers, Inc.; representative of newspapers in foreign countries Recipient, U.S. Cabot award, Columbia University; Commendator Order of Bernardo O'Higgins (Chile); Official Ordem Cruzeiro Do Sul (Brazil); gold medal, Pan American Society Author, Argentina's New Freedom
Biographical Note
Homer Lea
1876 November 17 Born, Denver, Colorado
1894-1896 Student, Occidental College, Los Angeles
1897-1900 Student, Stanford University
1900-1901 Lieutenant-General, Imperial Reform Army, China, under Kang Yu Wei, Grand President, Chinese Empire Reform Association
1900 Undertook relief of Kwang Hsu, Emperor of China
1902-1904 Organized Chinese military schools in U.S. and Chinese Imperial Army (C.I.A.)
1908 Author, The Vermillion Pencil
1909 Author, The Valor of Ignorance
1910-1912 Military adviser to Sun Yat-Sen
1912 Author, The Day of the Saxon
1912 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, telegrams, biographies, articles, pamphlets, clippings, writings, photographs, maps, scrapbooks, and memorabilia relating to Homer Lea, military adviser to Sun Yat-sen and author of The Valor of Ignorance, and to the revolutionary movement in China, circa 1900-1920. Includes writings and correspondence of Homer Lea, Ethel Lea, and Joshua B. Powers.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into six series: Correspondence of Homer Lea and Ethel Lea (Mrs. Homer Lea), Correspondence of Joshua B. Powers and Albert H. Powers, Collected Writings of Homer Lea, Collected Writings of Joshua B. Powers, Subject File, Miscellany, and Photographs.
Lea, Homer, 1876-1912.; Sun, Yat-sen, 1866-1925.; Americans--China.; China--History--20th century.; China--History--Revolution, 1911-1912.; Great Britain--Defenses.; United States--Defenses.
- Correspondence of Homer Lea and Ethel Lea (Mrs. Homer Lea), 1901-1929
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  - General (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Unidentified, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Addis, G. S., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Aishi, K., 1901 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Armstrong, General E., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Arthur, Sir Richard, 1911 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Belford, Robert J., 1910-1913 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Beresford, Sir Charles, 1912 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Bryant, Agnes, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Burton, General G. H., 1910-1912 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Cantlie, Mabel Barclay, 1912-1913(?) (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Chaffee, General Adna R., 1909-1912 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Chen, W. C., 1913 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Chockman, Jue, 1912 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Croxton, Major R. C., 1910 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Dawson, Sir Arthur Trevor, 1911 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Deitrick, James, 1911 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Dildman, Helene, 1913 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Duneka, F. A., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Everett, H. H., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - First National Bank of Los Angeles, 1912 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Gibbs, Major George W., 1905-1912 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Green, A. A., 1912 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Grenfeld, E. C., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Haig, Colonel H., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Hamilton, Sir Ian, 1910 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Hergesheimer, Joseph, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Herriman, George, 1911 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Hsueh, S. Y., 1903 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Hwang Hsing, 1914 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Ike, Koki H., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Imperial Maritime League, 1911 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Jamison, C. S., 1913 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Jarrett, Russell, 1913 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Jordan, David Starr, 1909-1910 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Joy, Florence J. M., 1913 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Kang Yu Wei, 1904 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Kennedy, J. Russell, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Kirtland, Capt. Harry B., 1912 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Lam, T. F., 1913 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Lea, Tom, 1912 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - Leighton, Sir Bryan, 1910 (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Lett, Harry Hom, 1904 (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - Leung Kwok, 1911 (Box-folder 1: 44)
  - The Lone Hand (periodical), 1911 (Box-folder 1: 45)
  - Long, Chaille, 1910-1912 (Box-folder 1: 46)
  - Lynne, E. O., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 47)
  - McCormick, Frederick, 1912-1929 (Box-folder 1: 48)
  - McIlvaine, Clarence W., 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1: 49)
  - Mande, Colonel F. N., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 50)
  - Maxim, Hudson, 1910-1912 (Box-folder 1: 51)
  - Newcome, W. A., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 52)
  - Newmark, Marco, 1903 (Box-folder 1: 53)
  - Ng Toy Kee, Dr., 1912 (Box-folder 1: 54)
  - Otis, H. G., 1909 (Box-folder 1: 55)
  - Overton, K. Z., undated (Box-folder 1: 56)
  - Phillips, John S., 1912 (Box-folder 1: 57)
  - Rhein, Lt. W. W., 1905 (Box-folder 1: 58)
  - Roberts, Field Marshal Lord Earl, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1: 59)
  - Root, Senator Elihu, 1911 (Box-folder 1: 60)
  - Shartle, Captain Samuel G., 1911 (Box-folder 1: 61)
  - Shelton, Major George H., 1910 (Box-folder 1: 62)
  - Shield, Dr., undated (Box-folder 1: 63)
  - Sinclair, Sir J. G.Tollemache, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1: 64)
  - Stanhope, Lord, 1911-1913 (Box-folder 1: 65)
  - Story, J. S., 1909 (Box-folder 1: 66)
  - Sun Fo, 1913-1918 (Box-folder 1: 67)
  - Sun Yat Sen, 1910-1922 (Box-folder 1: 68-69)
  - Swift, Major E. M., 1910 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Urbanek, Dr. M., 1912-1913 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Tillson, Lt.-Col. John O., 1911 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Van Loan, C. E., 1911 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Wan, B. C., 1913 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Warren, J. G., 1912-1913 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - White, Ermal Lea, 1913 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Willett, Tom Gear, 1912 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Wood, General Leonard, 1912 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Woodruff, Lt.-Col. Charles B., 1910 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Wrugel, Charles (?), 1912 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - York, Waldo M., 1903 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Yue Sen, 1912 (Box-folder 2: 13)
- Correspondence of Joshua B. Powers and Albert H. Powers, 1937-1962
  - Bemis, H. B., 1944 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Blackwelder, Justin, 1956-1961 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Britten, Milton R., 1957 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Chapin, Frederic, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Dinegar, Capt. W. W., 1958 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Frey, Agnes L., 1956 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Frick, Constance, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Glick, Carl, 1943-1957 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Hall, Josef W., 1925 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Harper & Brothers, 1957 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Hopper, Hedda, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Kates, Major Charles O., 1944-1955 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Lea, Howard P., 1944-1946 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Lesser, Julian, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Lewis, Boyd, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Newmark, Marco, 1937 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - O'Banion, Capt. Ansel E., 1943-1960 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Shenson, Walter, 1952 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Taylor, Betty (Mrs. Robert Taylor), 1944-1955 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Wilheim, Robert J., 1951-1952 (Box-folder 2: 33)
- Collected Writings of Homer Lea, 1906-1913
  Scope and Contents note
  Typewritten and handwritten drafts; carbon, mimeographed, and printed copies; outlines and notes; and correspondence, publishing contracts, book reviews, and royalty statements pertaining to books and articles, arranged alphabetically by title of manuscript.
  - Royalty statements and correspondence, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Untitled, undated (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - "Can China Fight?," The World Today, printed copy, 1907 (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - The Day of the Saxon (1912)
    - Typewritten first draft (Box-folder 2: 37)
    - Typewritten second draft, with handwritten notes and corrections (Box-folder 2: 38)
    - Correspondence, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 2: 39)
    - Publishing agreement (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - "The Defenses of China," two typewritten drafts, undated (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - "How Socialism Failed in China," Van Norden's Magazine, printed copy, 1908 (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - "The Legacy of Commodore Perry," North American Review, outline, printed copy, and correspondence, 1913 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "The Reawakening of China," outline and notes for unfinished book, 1906 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - "The Red Dawn of the New China," typewritten first draft, mimeographed copy of second draft, 1907 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - "A Romance of the Tombs," two typewritten drafts, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - The Valor of Ignorance (1909)
    - Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Publishing contract (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Reviews (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - "The Vandal," typewritten draft of unfinished story, 1911 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - The Vermillion Pencil (1908)
    - Partial handwritten draft (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Correspondence, 1908-1913 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- Collected Writings of Joshua Powers, 1961-1968(?)
  Drafts, newspaper articles, outlines and notes.
  - Untitled manuscript on life and works of Homer Lea, undated (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Biographical notes, typewritten draft, undated (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Newspaper articles on Homer Lea (extracts from manuscript), 1961 December (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Outline and typewritten draft on Homer Lea (Box-folder 3: 14)
- Subject File, 1905-1952
  Letters, articles, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, books, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Belford, Robert J., poems and letters, 1909 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - China, general (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - China, Republic of, government proclamations, 1911-1924(?) (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Chinese-American Educational Association, Articles of Agreement, 1905 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Chinese Exclusion Act, letter issued by Chinese Protective Association, Los Angeles, to U.S. Senators and Congressmen, 1912 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Chinese Imperial Army: Chinese military schools in the U.S.A. (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Chinese Revolution of 1911-1912 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Clowe, Clarence, State Capitalism in Ancient China, printed copy, 1911 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Defense of China and General Duvall's letter to President Theodore Roosevelt (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Evans, I. H., "The Latest Republic," The Watchman, printed copy, 1912 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Hwang Hsing (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - Kang Yu Wei (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Lea, Homer
    - Articles (Box-folder 3: 27)
    - Biographies
      - Newspaper clippings on Homer Lea's funeral in Taipei, 1969 (Box-folder 3: 28)
      - Carr, Harry, collected newspaper articles and interview transcripts, typewritten carbon copies, undated (Box-folder 3: 29)
      - Chapin, Frederic, unpublished biography, typewritten carbon copy, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 4: 1-5)
      - Dinegar, Capt. W. W. and Major Avery E. Kolb, "The Bitter Tea of Homer Lea," typewritten draft, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Letters, 1910-1912 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Medical report by Dr. M. Urbanek, 1912 April 6 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Liang Chi Chao (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - McIlvaine, Clarence W. (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - O'Banion, Capt. Ansel E., autobiographical statements, 1943 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Roberts, Field Marshal Lord Earl (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Sun Yat-Sen, speeches and writings, articles, letters, 1912-1920 (Box-folder 4: 13)
- Miscellany, 1908-1942
  Addresses, banknotes, calling cards, invitations, legal papers, maps, memorabilia, newspaper clippings, passport and scrapbooks, arranged as listed.
  - Addresses (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Banknotes, drafts, etc. (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Calling cards (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Invitations (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Legal papers (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Maps (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Membership cards (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Memorabilia (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Passport (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Scrapbooks, 2 volumes, 1908-1942 (Boxes 6-7, Map case)
  - Scrapbooks, 2 volumes, 1942 (Box 8)
- Photographs, circa 1876-1969
  145 photos, 7 duplicates, 24 negatives, 1 album, and 5 envelopes. Includes depictions of the Lea family, Chinese Imperial Army training, and China during the revolutionary period, as well as other images.
  - 9 photos of prominent Chinese intellectuals, such as Kan Yi Wei, Sun Yat-sen, Liang Chi Chao, and Chu Cho-wen, plus 5 negatives, circa 1900-1912 (Box-folder 5: A)
  - 11 photos and 6 duplicates plus 4 negatives of Homer Lea; 1 photo of the Lea family; 17 photos of friends and relatives, plus 1 duplicate, circa 1876-1912 (Box-folder 5: B)
  - 25 photos and 6 negatives depicting Chinese Imperial Army training in California, circa 1902-1910 (Box-folder 5: C)
  - 1 photo of Sun Yat-sen, signed, 1911 June 10 (Box-folder 7: mD)
  - 6 photos and 14 negatives of China, general (Box-folder 5: E)
  - 59 photos of China during the revolutionary period, 1910-1912 (Box 10)
    Album fF
  - 10 photos depicting Chinese Imperial Army training in California, circa 1902-1910 (Box 10)
  - 6 photos of Hwang Hsing with Ethel Lea (Mrs. Homer Lea) (Box 10)
  - 8 prints depicting the ceremonial placement of ashes of Homer Lea and Ethel Bryant Lea in the military cemetery in Taipei, Taiwan, 1969 April 20 (Box-folder 7: mG)